Leonard 你妈妈的飞机什么时候到?
Leonard, what time does your mom's plane get in?
不知道... 大概是明天早上
I don't know... some time tomorrow morning.
你不查查确切吗?
Don't you want to know for sure?
没必要 只要她进入加州上空
No need to. As soon as she flies into California airspace,
我就会感觉到原力受到干扰
I'll feel a disturbance in the Force.
你们的妈妈都飞过来看你们领奖
It's so nice both of your moms are coming in
真是太棒了
to see you guys get an award.
最早是我赢了双胞胎姐姐
Well, my mother's been there for every honor I've won
获得了"学会上厕所"桂冠
since I beat out my twin sister
之后每次领奖 妈妈肯定会到场
for the "did it on the potty" trophy.
看上去怎么样?
How does this look?
很漂亮 她肯定会喜欢的
Aw, it's so nice. She's gonna love it.
嗯 送妈妈的就是玫瑰
Sure, his mom gets roses.
我想要的时候
When I want them,
那就是"一束盛放的植物生殖器"
they're a "bouquet of severed plant genitals."
别说得像是情人节
You act like I didn't get you
我没送过你那根蘑菇木桩
that mushroom log on Valentine's Day.
他说得对
He's right.
玫瑰会枯死 但湿哒哒的烂木桩可以培养蘑菇
Roses die, but a moist rotting log will pump out mushrooms
长达两到三年之久
for two or three magical years.
要知道 你妈妈对我俩在一起
You know, your mom's never been
一向不是太高兴
too thrilled with our relationship.
也许我该给她准备份礼物 缓解一下关系
Maybe I should get her something so she warms up to me.
如果你立刻跑出去弄个博士学位
If you could run out and get a PhD,
可能她就会喜欢你了
that might make her like you.
真的吗? 她好像也不喜欢你呀
Really? It didn't work for you.
你觉得两位妈妈会相处融洽吗?
Do you think the moms will get along?
我不知道 她们挺不一样的
Uh, I don't know. They're pretty different.
也许她们会成为好朋友
Maybe they'll be best friends.
一个绝顶聪明 一个天真呆萌
One of them is brilliant, one is sweet and simple.
是不是听着很耳熟?
Sound familiar?
* 宇宙一度又烫又稠密 *
* Our whole universe was in a hot, dense state *
* 140亿年前终于爆了炸... 等着瞧! *
* Then nearly 14 billion years ago expansion started... Wait! *
* 地球开始降温 *
* The Earth began to cool *
* 自养生物来起哄 穴居人发明工具 *
* The autotrophs began to drool, Neanderthals developed tools *
* 我们建长城 我们建金字塔 *
* We built the Wall We built the pyramids *
* 数学 自然科学 历史 揭开神秘 *
* Math, Science, History, unraveling the mystery *
* 一切由大爆炸开始 *
* That all started with a big bang *
生活大爆炸 第八季第23集
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调: 酥酥期末要开挂
校对: UU养了只狐狸叫查理
翻译: 水晶影饺 豆腐脑 紫米薇饼 柚子睡懒觉 凤梨酥
Shelly 你和Leonard能得这个奖 我真为你们自豪
Shelly, I'm so proud of you and Leonard for getting this award.
谢谢你 妈妈
Oh, thank you, Mother.
我试着看了下你的论文 但发现
I tried to read your paper, but it was very hard
很难理解
for me to understand.
事实上非常简单易懂
Oh, it's quite straightforward, actually.
它阐述了一个新的宇宙模型
It describes a new model of the universe
概念上来说 可以看成是
that conceptualizes it as the surface
n维的超流体的表面
of an n-dimensional superfluid.
真有趣
Interesting.
这东西你相信
You can believe that,
但上帝让动物一对对上方舟 那就是胡扯
but God filling an ark with animals two-by-two is nonsense.
他们拿什么喂狮子 妈妈?
What did they feed the lions, Mother?
当然是淹死的罪人的浮尸
The floating bodies of drowned sinners, of course.
听着 Leonard的妈妈是位著名的精神病医生
Listen, Leonard's mom is a renowned psychiatrist
以及女科学家
and woman of science.
她在场的时候 你能不能不要
Can you please keep the Bible babble to yourself
圣经来圣经去的?
while she's here?
你觉得我丢你脸了吗?
Are you ashamed of me?
当然不是 我爱你
Of course not. I love you.
我只是觉得你的信仰和言行会让我难堪
I'm just embarrassed by the things you believe, do and say.
我也爱你
Well, I love you, too.
我的可爱小狮子狗
My little bowl of lion chow.
你和Penny定了婚礼时间吗?
So, have you and Penny set a wedding date?
没有 我们想慢慢来
No, we're kind of taking it slow.
好吧
I see.
那是什么意思?
What does that mean?
你和这个女人分分合合七年了
You've been on and off with this woman for seven years
订婚都已经一年了
and engaged for one year.
我肯定会猜想是不是出问题了
One has to wonder if there's a problem.
你们的性关系和谐吗?
Are you having satisfactory intercourse?
是的 妈妈
Yes, Mother.
看出来了 也就和谐而已
Only satisfactory. I see.
我改答案了
I change my answer.
性生活... 很棒 很火辣
It... it's amazing. It's hot.
我们如胶似漆 根本分不开
We can barely keep our hands off each other.
在你妈妈面前强调自己高超的性爱技术
Seems odd to try and impress your mother
真是太奇怪了
with your sexual prowess.
不过 你的恋母情结总是无法得以解决
But then, you always did have that unresolved Oedipal complex.
听着 就是你刚刚那样
See, this right here, what you're doing,
你能别在Sheldon的妈妈耳边说这些话吗?
Can you please not do that around Sheldon's mom?
为什么? 你也喜欢她么?
Why? Are you attracted to her, too?
当然没有
Of course not.
她只不过是一个信奉上帝的很贴心的一个人
She's... she's just a very sweet and God-fearing lady,
你得尊重她的宗教信仰
and you have to be respectful of her beliefs.
Leonard 我是成年人了
Leonard, I'm an adult.
我知道如何在不同生活背景的人
I know how to conduct myself around people
面前表现自己
from different walks of life.
谢谢你
Thank you.
她是从哪里来的来着?
Where is she from again?
- 德州东部  - 天哪
- East Texas.  - Ugh.
嗨 看看谁来了
Hey, look who's here.
啊 是Hofstadter博士啊 真高兴再次看到你
Oh, Dr. Hofstadter, it's so good to see you again.
我也是
Likewise.
我读过你的论文了 非常不错
I read your paper, it was very impressive.
是吗 谢谢
Oh, thank you.
我们刚才路上堵了两个小时车
We just spent two hours in traffic.
你有想过跟我说你喜欢我们的论文吗?
Did you think to mention to me that you liked our paper?
当然 但是母亲的职责就是
Of course I did, but it's a mother's job
确保她的孩子的自尊心不会依赖于
to make sure her child's self-esteem is not dependent
任何人的认可
on anyone's approval.
你真好 居然认为我还有自尊心
That's so sweet, you think I have self-esteem.
Hofstadter博士 这是我的母亲 Mary
Dr. Hofstadter, I want you to meet my mother, Mary.
很高兴见到你
So nice to meet you.
我也是 你的旅途怎么样?
Nice to meet you, too. How was your flight?
不错 你呢?
Very pleasant. And yours?
非常好 几乎像是
Lovely. Almost as if someone
上帝
飞机被"某个人"照看着
not saying who was watching over the plane.
你是开玩笑吧?
You're kidding, right?
你还真是婉转啊 妈 婉转
Subtle, mom, real subtle.
Sutart啊
Stuart.
早啊
Morning.
我们之前谈过了
We talked about this.
我不介意你继续住在这里
I don't mind you still living here
但是我们有家规啊
but we got to have some rules.
第一条就是必须穿裤子
And rule number one is pants.
早啊
Hey.
你一定很为你的儿子骄傲吧
You must be very proud of your son.
那当然
Oh, yes.
他最近在最高法院上辩护了一个案子
He recently argued a case before the Supreme Court.
真的吗?
He did?
哦 你是说这个儿子吗?
Oh, you mean this son?
当然 他这么棒
Uh, sure, he's terrific.
Beverly 你想不想看我推导出来的
Uh, Beverly, would you like to see the math I worked out
证明我们的猜想的数学公式呢?
to support our hypothesis?
嗯 你是说我的猜想吗
Uh, you mean, my hypothesis.
它完全是由我自己提出来的
I hypothesized it all by myself.
别激动 孩子
Calm down, dear.
Mary 我很好奇
Mary, I'm curious.
你是什么时候注意到
When did you first realize
你的儿子有一个如此聪明的大脑呢?
that your son had such a remarkable mind?
哦 问的好
Ooh, good question.
每个人都喜欢听天才少年Sheldon Cooper的故事
Everyone loves stories about Sheldon Cooper, boy genius.
我想 是从他13岁时
Well, I would have to say when he was 13
尝试在工具棚里建造核反应堆的那一刻开始的
and tried to build a nuclear reactor in the tool shed.
哦 这个特别不错
Ooh, this is a good one.
你首先要了解 Shelly这孩子
Now, the first thing you have to know about Shelly is
自打他小时候
ever since he was a little boy
他一直关心别人的福祉
he was always concerned with the well-being of others.
他觉得交电费
And he didn't think that it was fair
是一件很不公平的事
for people to pay for electricity.
所以他想要给整个小镇的人提供免费的电力
So he was gonna power the entire town for free.
放射性元素 可以被用做核反应堆燃料棒
给她讲那个铀的故事!
Tell her about the uranium!
给她讲那个关于铀的故事!
Tell her about the uranium.
哦 好吧
Oh, well.
这个故事很好玩
Oh, this is adorable.
黄饼: 核反应燃料重铀酸胺或重铀酸钠的俗称
当他想从Chad(音同乍得 非洲国家)那里弄到黄饼时
When he arranged to get some yellowcake from Chad
我以为他是在谈论他从他的朋友那里
I thought he was talking about Twinkies
拿的Twinkies面包
from one of his friends.
美国著名夹心面包 其公司现已破产
但其实我不是
But I wasn't.
因为我根本没朋友
'Cause I didn't have any friends.
不
No.
最后我才发现这个淘气包是在试着
It turns out that this little scallywag was trying
用我的Visa卡从一个
to use my Visa card to buy uranium
乍得的军阀那里买铀!
from an African warlord in the country of Chad!
听起来Sheldon很调皮啊
Sounds like Sheldon was a handful.
当然难啊
Oh, he was a handful.
我那时确实很调皮
I was a handful.
你现在还不是一样
You still are.
呃 妈 给Mary讲讲
Uh, Mom, hey, tell Mary the story
用来产生静电的装置
我用吸尘器做了个Van de Graaff起电机
about how I made a Van de Graaff generator
的那个故事
out of our vacuum cleaner.
好吧
All right.
他把吸尘器给弄坏了
He broke the vacuum cleaner.
有一阵子就是 吸血鬼吸血鬼吸血鬼
I mean, for a while, everything was vampires.
现在全是僵尸了
Now it's all zombies.
不知道下一次会流行什么样的怪物
I wonder what the next monster fad will be.
倒是很久没看到什么优质的隐形人了
We haven't had a good invisible man in a while.
看来 你们从来没见过我想搭讪女人的囧样
Clearly, you've never seen me try to talk to a woman.
大哥们
Guys.
你们坐在这儿玩游戏的时候
In the time you've been sitting here playing video games,
我把车给洗了 顺手买了清洁用品
I got the car washed, picked up cleaning supplies
还去了银行
and went to the bank.
我把裤子穿上了
I put on pants.
马屁精
Kiss-ass.
好吧 不知道从什么时候开始我变成
Okay, I don't know when I became the mother
三个懒娃的老妈了
to three lazy teenagers,
但是就到今天为止了
but it stops today.
我命令你们几个去打扫厨房 要彻底清理
You guys are cleaning the kitchen, top to bottom.
嘿 我又不住这儿
Hey, I don't even live here.
那你说 我洗衣机里有没有你衣服?
Yes or no, do you have clothes in my laundry right now?
确实有
I do.
有些是羊毛的
And some of it's wool,
所以如果可能的话请把它们平铺晾干
so dry flat if possible.
哦 这是我拿到
Oh, and here's a picture of me receiving
本科学位时候的照片
my bachelor of science degree.
你看起来不是很开心的样子
You don't look very happy.
嗯 我刚开始青春期
Well, I had just begun puberty.
正是我这辈子里最容易发毛
It was figuratively and literally
也最容易长毛的时候
one of the hairiest moments of my life.
Shelly不喜欢改变
Shelly does not like change.
哦 是的
Oh, true.
但是 再怎么千辛万苦的打它
But all the clenching in the world will not keep
睾丸还是会奋力挤出腹部
testicles in your abdomen.
嘿 不好意思 工作上有点事情耽误了
Hey, sorry, got caught up at work.
嗨 Beverly!
Hi, Beverly!
你好
Hello.
哦 好吧
Oh, okay.
不好意思 我忘了
Sorry, I forgot.
你还记得我妈吧
You remember my mother.
哦 是的 嗨 Mary!
Oh, yes. Hi, Mary!
再见到你很高兴 亲爱的
Good to see you again, dear.
啊 对 这才对嘛
Ah, yeah, now that's what I'm talking about.
妈 我和Penny订婚之后你就没见过她了
So, Mom, you haven't seen Penny since we got engaged.
哦 是啊 给你看我的戒指
Oh, yeah, let me show you the ring.
哦 挺可爱的
Oh, lovely.
一定很贵吧
Must have been very expensive.
哦 不 一点都不贵
Oh, no, not at all.
不 我们在网上找到一个
No, we, uh, found a place online
可以把金刚石钻头稍作修改的地方
that, uh, repurposes diamond drill bits.
不是 他说的不是真的
We did not. That's not true.
我能跟你单独谈一会儿么?
Can I speak to you alone for a second?
哦 可以
Oh, sure.
戒指是蒂凡尼的
It came from Tiffany's.
你是说盒子 是吗?
You mean the box, right?
快走!
Keep walking!
他在戒指上花了多少钱我真的不在意
Really doesn't matter to me how much he spent on the ring.
我觉得
I think.
戒指的事我说错了吗?
Did I misspeak about the ring?
是啊 这个我们待会儿说
Yes, and we'll get back to that.
但是 呃 在你妈都在这里的情况下
But, uh, even with your mother here,
你还是故意把我妈的注意力全都吸引过去了
you are deliberately hogging all the attention from my mom.
你就像那种
You're like one of those elephant seal pups
从两个妈妈那里偷吸母乳的小海象!
that steals the milk from two mothers!
你是指海洋生物学家
Do you mean what marine biologists
所说的那种"超级断奶"现象吗?
refer to as "super weaning"?
是 你是一个超级断奶娃!
Yes, you are a super weaner!
嗯 现在我不得不纠正你一下
Well, now I have to correct you.
作为多少懂一点海象知识的人
A-As a bit of an elephant seal buff,
我认为更精准的比方
the more accurate comparison
应该是两只母海象
would be when two mother seals
都积极地试图哺育同一只小海象
actively seek to nourish the same pup.
所以 我认为你想用的术语
So I believe the term you're looking for
应该是双母吸奶娃
is a double mother suckler.
是 你说对了
Yeah, you're right.
我要说的就是这个
That is the term I'm looking for.
你就是个卑鄙的双母吸奶娃!
You are a dirty double mother suckler!
终于把这个术语搞清了
Okay, well, now that we have the terminology straightened out.
你哪来的胆子!
How dare you!
我们不着急
We're not in a rush.
到时候挑个好日子
We'll set a date when the time is right.
亲爱的 这不重要
It doesn't matter, sweetie.
男女结合之时
The moment a man lays with a woman,
上帝眼里 你们已是夫妻了
they are married in the eyes of the Lord.
我去
Uch.
"我去"?
"Uch"?
圣经在你看来就是一句"我去"?
The bible is "uch" to you?
不好意思
No, I'm sorry.
我失礼了
That was inappropriate.
作为精神学专家
As a psychiatrist, I know how important
我深知迷信对人的重要性
people's superstitions can be to them.
你想说说迷信?
You want to talk about superstitions?
Sheldon给过我你写的书...
Sheldon sent me the books you wrote...
都是什么超我什么本能冲动的鬼话
all that nonsense about superegos and ids.
这是什么鬼人说的?
What bull dropped that on the barn floor?
他叫西格蒙德·弗洛伊德
His name is Sigmund Freud.
哇 看啊!
Hey, look at that!
你俩都相信大胡子犹太人
You both believe in Jewish bearded guys.
你一边待着
Stay out of this.
好的
Mm-hmm.
起码我相信的大胡子宣扬的是
At least the bearded man that I believe in
爱和慈悲
preaches love and compassion.
你那个说的都是
All yours talks about is
我们为什么把大便憋回去
why you hold in your poop
而且想爬回妈妈的肚子里
and want to crawl back inside your mama.
有意思
It's fascinating.
你这样的人怎么能生出
How can someone as enlightened as Sheldon
Sheldon这么聪明的孩子?
come from someone like you?
我知道为什么
I know the answer.
你可能不会喜欢的
You're not gonna like it.
说说看
Try me.
当时我怀着Shelly 去教堂的路上
When I was pregnant with Shelly, I was driving to church,
我向上帝祈祷
and I was praying to the Lord
赐我一个比他那傻爹聪明的孩子吧
to give me a son smarter than his dumb-ass daddy.
接着就看见旁边一辆斯巴鲁里
And I looked over and I saw a Jesus bobblehead
有个耶稣摇头娃娃在向我点头
in the Subaru next to me nodding yes.
这几个意思?
What is that supposed to mean?
我想说 真不敢相信我在跟你说这个
It means... I can't believe we're having this conversation.
那多做几次
Well, do it some more.
说不定能拍出点灵感
Maybe you can knock some sense into yourself.
我们还是还是别自残了
Why don't we all stops hitting ourselves
说点和谐的话题 比如
and talk about something safe, you know,
鞋子啊或者可爱的中国小娃娃
like shoes or how cute little Chinese babies are.
你妈更喜欢我不喜欢你
It is not my fault that your mother likes me
- 那也不能赖我啊!  - 别给自己脸上贴金了!
- better than she likes you!  - Oh, don't flatter yourself!
她喜欢谁都比喜欢我多!
She likes everybody better than she likes me!
这果冻放多久了?
How old is this Jell-O?
其实这是胡萝卜 所以很久了
Well, it's carrots, so gonna say very.
抱歉 你们要做这些
Sorry we have to do this.
Bernadette说的也没错
Bernadette's not wrong.
她确实忙里忙外的
She does work hard around here.
也许她不再把你当孩子一样照顾
Yeah, maybe it's a good thing
也是件好事
if she stops babying you so much.
她没把我当孩子
She doesn't baby me.
我上次看见她用平板车拉你回家
I saw her pull you home in a wagon.
澄清一下
For your information,
我是追一辆冰激凌车的时候扭了脚
I twisted my ankle chasing the ice cream truck.
承认吧哥们 Bernadette确实像你妈妈一样对你
Face it, dude, Bernadette treats you the same way
这样的夫妻关系可不健康
your mother used to, and that was not a healthy relationship.
你说得对
You're right.
是时候了
It's time for me
我要在婚姻里表现得成熟一点
to act like an adult in this marriage.
担起一个丈夫的责任 把垃圾扔出去
Starting with my husbandly duty of taking out the trash.
Bernie 我闯祸了!
Bernie, I made a mess!
真抱歉我让你妈生气了
I'm terribly sorry that I upset your mother.
没事 她会原谅你的
Oh, it's all right. She'll forgive you.
不原谅是要下地狱的
She has to or she goes to hell.
我发现我的育儿策略
I can't help but notice
和你妈妈对你无条件的爱比起来
how her unconditional love for you
完全不一样啊
is diametrically opposed to my own parenting strategies.
这种把感情作为奖励
Well, you doled out affection
施舍给孩子的方法...
as a reward for achievement...
被证实是养育孩子的良方
a proven way to raise a child.
也是训练小白鼠的良方
Or train a rat.
可是你看你现在多优秀啊
But look how well you turned out.
我好想假装谦虚一下 不过谁信啊?
I'd feign modesty at this point, but who would believe me?
而且 您还应该想想
Still, you need to consider
Leonard的兄弟姐妹们都很成功啊
how successful Leonard's brother and sister are.
也是啊
I suppose.
可是我的兄弟姐妹是一群蠢货
While my brother and sister are mouth-breathing idiots.
如果 你成长在一个以奖励机制为基础的环境中
Do you suppose you would've flourished more
你会不会有更好的发展呢?
in a reward-based environment?
或许会吧
Perhaps.
可是不管我什么时候想吃切成段的热狗和意面 我妈都会给我做
But my mom made me spaghetti with chopped-up hot dogs
所以 我也不在乎了
whenever I wanted, so who cares?
我做自己的时候 我妈从来不会对我表达出爱和关注
Not once did my mother ever give me any love or affection
我必须得努力赢的她的爱
for just being myself; I always had to earn it.
哦 Leonard
Oh, Leonard,
她肯定也是很爱你的
I'm sure she loves you very much.
只不过是用她的冷冰冰的背弃上帝的方法
In her own cold godless way.
是啊 而且你也不用通过努力得到我的爱
Yeah, and you certainly don't have to earn my love.
谢了
Thank you.
不过大概你给我买这个
Of course, you already knew that
公主方形切割钻头的时候就知道了
when you bought me this princess-cut drill bit.
真的不是这么回事
That's not what it is.
我知道 我知道
I know, I know.
等你妈妈回来 我会向她道歉
When your mom gets back, I'm gonna need
我不该那样对她说话的
to apologize for the way I spoke to her.
不用吧 是她挑起来的
Well, come on now, she did kind of start it.
这不重要 一名合格的基督徒总是体谅他人
Doesn't matter; a good Christian would've turned the other cheek.
不过
On the other hand,
一个合格的德州人早一枪崩了她 所以...
a good Texan would've shot her, so...
我只能折中一下了
I just kind of split the difference.
嘿 谁想吃意面和热狗?
Hey, who's in the mood for spaghetti and hot dogs?
- 我要吃!  - 我也要!
- Oh, me!  - Yeah, me, too!
马上就好啦
Coming up.
我觉得我根本不配吃这么好吃的
I don't really feel I deserve it.
刚才可真是一团乱
That was a big sticky mess,
但是... 我搞定了
but... I think I got it.
- 看起来不错  - 是啊
- Looks good.  - Yeah.
看啊
Look at that.
你自己清理干净了
You cleaned it up all by yourself.
是啊 我自己收拾好了
Yes, I cleaned it up all by myself.
说实话 我真不知道你为什么一直在抱怨...
Honestly, I don't know why you complain so...
好吧 我可能漏了这块地方
Okay, maybe I missed one spot.
你先出去
Just leave.
我很高兴我们能
I'm so glad that you and I were able
- 放下分歧握手言和  - 我也是
- to bury the hatchet.  - Me, too.
我尊重你有自己信仰的权利
And I respect your right to your beliefs.
我也会为你祈祷的
And I will pray for you.
好了老妈 趁现在没人吵架
Okay, Mom, let's get you back to your hotel
我赶紧送你回酒店吧
before anyone says anything else.
稍等一下
One moment.
我有话想跟你说
There's something I need to say to you.
真的? 完了完了
Oh, really? That's too bad.
Leonard 你一直要通过努力来得到我的爱和关注
Leonard, I always made you earn my affection,
不过今天我意识到
but today I realize
教育孩子的方法不止这一种
that there's more than one way to raise a child.
是我告诉她的!
I taught her that!
所以 我想
Therefore, I would like
开始以一种新的方法...
to initiate a new protocol wherein I...
无条件地爱你
shower you with unconditional love.
哇哦
Wow.
从什么时候开始?
When does that start?
还是这么粘人
So needy.
过来让妈妈抱抱
Come to Mommy.
没事的 快过去吧
It's okay, go ahead.
我的儿啊
Oh, my son.
我的妈啊
Oh, my mother.
我的上帝啊
Oh, my God.
# 生活如此艰难 #
# It's a hard-knock life #
# 我们的生活如此艰难 #
# It's the hard-knock life for us #
# 无人真心相待 一直被欺骗 #
# 'Stead of treated, we get tricked #
# 无人亲吻我 还总被人踹 #
# 'Stead of kisses, we get kicked #
# 生活如此艰难 #
# It's the hard-knock life #
# 满心痛苦 无人倾诉 #
# Got no folks to speak of so #
# 我们挥起锄头 面对生活的艰苦 #
# It's the hard-knock row we hoe #
# 没有羊毛毯 只有旧棉被  #
#  Cotton blankets, 'stead of wool #
# 从来吃不饱 顿顿饿得慌 #
# Empty bellies, 'stead of full #
# 生活如此艰难 #
# It's a hard-knock life. #